<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief account concerning several of the agents of New-England, their negotiation at the Court of England with some remarks on the new charter granted to the colony of Massachusets shewing that all things duely considered, greater priviledges than what are therein contained, could not at this time rationally be expected by the people there.</title>
            <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12677660</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12677660</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65598</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 794:31 or 1531:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief account concerning several of the agents of New-England, their negotiation at the Court of England with some remarks on the new charter granted to the colony of Massachusets shewing that all things duely considered, greater priviledges than what are therein contained, could not at this time rationally be expected by the people there.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Increase Mather.</note>
                  <note>This item can be found at reels 794:31 and 1531:7.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through; copy at reel 1531:7 is stained, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Harvard University Library and Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  New Plymouth, 1620-1691.</term>
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  Politics and government --  1620-1691.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65598:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65598:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF ACCOUNT CONCERNING Several of the AGENTS OF New-England, THEIR NEGOTIATION at the COURT OF ENGLAND: WITH Some REMARKS on the NEW CHARTER Granted to the Colony of <hi>MASSACH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SETS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING That all things duely Conſidered, Greater Priviledges than what are therein contained, could not at this Time rationally be expected by the People there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:65598:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65598:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEF ACCOUNT CONCERNING Several of the AGENTS OF <hi>NEW-ENGLAND,</hi> THEIR NEGOTIATION at the COURT of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I May rationally ſuppoſe that an Account of my Negotiation in <hi>England,</hi> where I have been attending the great Affair of <hi>New-England</hi> for more than Three Years, will be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me.</p>
            <p>When I began my Voyage from <hi>Boſton</hi> for <hi>London</hi> (which was in <hi>April,</hi> 1688.) <hi>New-England</hi> was in a very deplorable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He that was then Governour there, acted by an Illegal and Arbitrary Commiſſion; and invaded Liberty and Property after ſuch a manner, as no man could ſay any thing was his own. Wiſe men believed it to be a neceſſary Duty to uſe all Lawful means to obtain ſome Relief and Remedy againſt thoſe growing Evils. This could not be done, without firſt acquainting him who was then in the Throne, with the miſerable State of his Subjects in that Territory. No man of common Prudence could be inſenſible of the Hazard and Danger that woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tend his Perſon and Family, in appearing at Court as a Complainant againſt a Governour that was King <hi>James</hi> his Creature.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65598:3"/>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, being encouraged by many of the principal Gentlemen in <hi>New-England,</hi> I reſolved to venture, thô I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the Attempt, rather than to ſee my Countrey ruin'd.</p>
            <p>In <hi>June</hi> following, I had the favour of waiting on the late King: I muſt acknowledge he was very kind and Obliging in his Expreſſions, giving me Liberty of Acceſs in private to him whenever I deſired it; ſeeming to wonder at the things I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with, and profeſſing that no man in the World ſhould be more ready to relieve the People Interceded for, than he would. Notwithſtanding which, nothing was done for them all that Summer. And indeed, good words were as much as any one under my Character had reaſon to expect in King <hi>James</hi> his Court.</p>
            <p>At the time of the happy Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> (being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the Right Honourable my Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> of whoſe kindneſs all <hi>New-England</hi> has cauſe to be ſenſible; his Lordſhip having upon all Occaſions concerned himſelf for them) I made my humble Addreſſes to his preſent Majeſty (then <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi>) in behalf of that Countrey. There was a Circular Letter drawn up to be ſent to all the Plantations, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to <hi>New-England,</hi> to confirm thoſe Governours in their Places till further Order. Mr. <hi>Jephſon</hi> (the then Princes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary) ſhewed me the Letter. I aſſured him that <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would be undone, if that Letter ſhould come to them: Within a few dayes he told me that he had acquainted His Highneſs with what I ſaid to him: Who had thereupon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him not to tranſmit that Letter to <hi>New-England;</hi> But to all the other Plantations where there were Proteſtant Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. This was certainly an happy turn for <hi>New England.</hi> How would their Oppreſſors have inſulted over them, had ſuch a Letter come into their hands! I knew that whileſt that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple enjoyed their Old Charter they proſpered wonderfully: But that ſince they were deprived of the Priviledges therein contained, their ruins were multiplyed; and that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants were generally deſirous of being reſettled as in the days of Old: for which cauſe I reſolved to do what was in me that it might be ſo.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65598:3"/>
            <p>Whenever I had the Honour of ſpeaking to the King, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>White-Hall, Hampton-Court,</hi> or <hi>Kenſington,</hi> I ſtill mention'd the Charter, and always found that the King (although he judged it would be for the Advantage of <hi>New-England,</hi> to have a Covernor Commiſſion'd by his Majeſty, yet that he) was graciouſly inclin'd to Reſtore Charter-Priviledges unto his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in that Territory. Once, at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> his Majeſty was pleaſed to bid me reſt aſſured, that it ſhould be ſo, if it were in his Power to cauſe it to be done. I adviſed with many wiſe Men about this momentous Affair, whoſe Judgment was, That the beſt, and moſt effectual Courſe would be, to endeavour a <hi>Reverſion of the Judgment</hi> againſt the Charter of the <hi>Maſſachuſets,</hi> by an Act of Parliament; and after that, to Petition the King for ſuch additional Priviledges as ſhould be thought needful. I prayed Sir <hi>Henry Aſhurſt,</hi> whom I knew to be a worthy Member of the Convention (as well as of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) Parliament, to concern himſelf for the good People in that Countrey: Which he did without much intreaty, being of himſelf forward to do Good: Nor is it poſſible for <hi>New-England</hi> ever duely to Recompenſe him for his ſincere Intentions, and aſſiduous Endeavours to ſerve them. We both of us ſpake to many of the principal leading Men in that Parliament: The Iſſue of which, was, The <hi>Commons of England</hi> Voted the Taking away the <hi>Charters</hi> belonging to <hi>New-England</hi> (as of thoſe in <hi>England</hi>) to be Illegal, and a Grievance, and that they ought to be Reſtored. A Bill was drawn up accordingly, which Paſſed the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and was ſent to the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, on <hi>January</hi> the Tenth, 1689. A great Intereſt, in behalf of <hi>New-England,</hi> had been made amongſt the Lords; but that Parliment being unexpectedly Prorogu'd and Diſſolv'd, a whole Year's <hi>Siſyphean Labour</hi> came to nothing.</p>
            <p>When this preſent Parliament met, it was, for ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, thought not adviſeable to trouble them with the Affair of <hi>New-England.</hi> Some Eſſays were then made, to ſee if by a <hi>Writ of Error in Judgment,</hi> the Caſe relating to the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> might be brought out of <hi>Chancery</hi> into the <hi>Kings-Bench.</hi> But an unexpected Providence rendred an Attempt of that Nature vain. Never did I ſee a more ſignal Hand of Heaven in any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65598:4"/>Matter, than in Diſappointing all Deſigns, and Fruſtrating all Hopes for Obtaining the ſo much deſired full <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of all Charter-Priviledges, by a <hi>Reverſion</hi> of the Judgment entred againſt them. There was now but one way left for the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of <hi>New-England, ſc.</hi> To implore the King's Royal Favour.</p>
            <p>It was not in the King's Power to Reverſe the Judgment againſt the Old Charter; nevertheleſs, his Majeſty had Power to Re-incorporate his Subjects, thereby granting them a New Charter, which ſhould contain all the Old, with New, and more Ample Priviledges.</p>
            <p>This, Three of the <hi>Agents</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for; the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Monmouth</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to deliver that Petition with his own Noble Hand. After which, through the Interceſſion of a Great and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſonage, the King was graciouſly pleaſed to referr the Affair of <hi>New-England</hi> to the Conſideration of the two Chief Juſtices, with his Majeſty's Attorney, and Sollicitor-General. They Four met three or four times: They were ſo kind as to give me leave to be preſent with them at all their Conſultations. The Heads of the Charter belonging to the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony,</hi> and of that granted to Sir <hi>Ferdinando Gorges,</hi> were preſented in Writing; together with what additional Priviledges we did at preſent pray for. They all thought there was nothing Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable or Prejudicial to the King's Intereſt in what was requeſted. Theſe things were preſented to the King by my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Holt.</hi> The King ordered him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to the Council; which was done on the Firſt of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> laſt; when they were referred to the Conſideration of the Right Honourable the Lords of the Committee for Foreign Plantations.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon this, the King began his Royal Voyage for <hi>Holland;</hi> untill whoſe Happy Return nothing could be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected as to the Settlement of <hi>New-England.</hi> In the mean time, I drew up ſeveral Reaſons for the Confirmation of Charter-Priviledges granted to the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony;</hi> which I diſperſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65598:4"/>among the Lords of his Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and did particularly addreſs my ſelf to the greateſt part of them, humbly praying their Lorſhips Favour to <hi>New-England,</hi> in a Matter which ſeemed ſo Juſt and Equitable: And had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from many of them, that whenever the Affair of <hi>New-England</hi> ſhould come before the Council-Board, they would do what in them was, that <hi>Ancient Rights and Priviledges might be Reſtored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, a Noble Perſonage did me the Honour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce me to the Queen, that ſo I might have an Opportunity to ſollicit Her Majeſty's Royal Favour towards her Subjects in <hi>New-England.</hi> I aſſured her Majeſty, That there are none better affected to their Majeſties Government, and that on that account they had been expoſed to the Rage of the <hi>French,</hi> and other Enemies to the preſent Government in <hi>England;</hi> and that the King having referred the Conſideration of the Affair of <hi>New-England</hi> to the two Chief Juſtices, with the Attorney and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor-General; we only prayed, that what they thought was reaſonable, might be granted to us.</p>
            <p>The Queen graciouſly replied, That <hi>that was a reaſonable Requeſt, and that ſhe hoped it would be done for us, only it could not be done but by the Council.</hi> Her Majeſty moreover aſſured me, That ſhe had divers times ſpoken to the King in behalf of <hi>New-England;</hi> and that, <hi>for her own part, ſhe deſired that that People might not only have what was</hi> Juſt <hi>done for them, but that ſomething of</hi> Favour <hi>might be ſhown to them.</hi>— I the rather mention this, that ſo all <hi>New-England</hi> may be excited to Pray for ſo Gracious a <hi>Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>King</hi> returned to <hi>England,</hi> he ſtayed not there above a Fortnight: In which time I had twice the Honour to wait on his Majeſty in behalf of <hi>New-England.</hi> The Firſt time I only delivered the laſt <hi>Addreſs</hi> from the <hi>General-Court</hi> at <hi>Boſton, viz.</hi> that of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. 1690. and a <hi>Petition</hi> from many Merchants in <hi>London,</hi> praying, That Charter-Priviledges might be reſtored to <hi>New-England;</hi> and that ſome Frigats might be ſent for the Security of thoſe Coaſts. The Second time, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65598:5"/>prayed the Continuance of his Royal Favour to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in that Territory. The King was then pleaſed to ask me, What I would have to be done for <hi>New-England?</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">I humbly put his Majeſty in mind of our Old Charter-Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: And that if they ſhould, by his Royal Favour and Goodneſs, he reſtored, that would make his Majeſty's <hi>Name</hi> Great in thoſe Ends of the Earth, as long as the World ſhould ſtand: That none of his Subjects prayed more for his Royal Perſon, and for the Succeſs of his Arms, than they did: That they were all of them Proteſtants, and that they differed in leſſer Matters from ſome others, being of thoſe that were called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Congregational-Men:</hi> That his Majeſty, in his great Wiſdom, had conſidered the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>England,</hi> and the Circumſtances of <hi>Scotland:</hi> That, according to his Royal Wiſdom, he would conſider the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of <hi>New-England</hi> alſo; and that ſuch Rulers would not be agreeable to them, as were very proper to the other <hi>Engliſh Plantations.</hi>
               </q> The King replied to me, That within two or three days he expected a <hi>Report</hi> from the Committee of Lords, for <hi>Foreign Plantations,</hi> and that he ſhould then ſee what could be done.</p>
            <p>Two days after this, (<hi>viz.</hi> on <hi>April</hi> the 30th. 1691.) it was by the Lords of the Committee propoſed to the King, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would have the People in <hi>New-England</hi> make what Laws, and appoint what Officers They pleaſed? Or, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther He would not appoint a Governour of his own, who ſhould have a Negative Voice on all Acts of Government? The King was very inquiſitive to know whether he might, without any Breach of Law, ſet a Governor over that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony: (For we have a King now that will not Act contrary to Law.) The <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice,</hi> and ſome other of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, anſwer'd, That whatever might be the Merit of the Cauſe, inaſmuch as the Charter of <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony,</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> ſtood vacated by a Judgment againſt them, it was certainly in the King's Power to put them under what Form of Government he ſhould think beſt for them. The King then ſaid, That he was deſirous to promote the Welfare of <hi>New-England,</hi> as well as of <hi>England;</hi> and that he believed it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65598:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>would be for the Good and Advantage of his Subjects in that Colony, to be under a Governour appointed by himſelf: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, That he would have the Agents of <hi>New-England</hi> Nominate a Perſon that ſhould be agreeable to the Temper and Incllnations of the People there; only that, at this time, it was neceſſary that a Military Man ſhould be ſet over them; and that this notwithſtanding, he would have Charter-Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges Reſtored and Confirmed to them.</p>
            <p>The next day, the King began his Second Royal Voyage for <hi>Holland;</hi> but an <hi>Order of Council</hi> was drawn up, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, That it was the King's Pleaſure to have a Governour of his own Appointing ſent to <hi>New-England,</hi> who ſhould have a Negative Voice in all Acts of Government: And, That the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony</hi> ſhould be ſettled on the ſame Foundation with <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> &amp;c. And that a Charter ſhould be prepared accordingly. As ſoon as I had a Copy of this <hi>Order of Council,</hi> I went with it to four or five of the Lords of His Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy-Council: Every one of which, ſaid, That as it was worded, it did not (in their Opinion) agree with the King's Expreſſions or Intentions. Moreover, I cauſed a Copy of this Order to be tranſmitted to my Lord <hi>Sidney,</hi> one of his Majeſty's Principal Secretaries of State, then with the King in <hi>Flanders;</hi> praying, That if that Order, Signed by one of the Clerks of the Council, was not according to the King's Mind, His Majeſty would graciouſly pleaſe to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his Diſ-approbation thereof: But no ſuch Signification ever came.</p>
            <p>The Attorney-General, in the mean time, prepared a Draught of a Charter, according to what he took to be the King's Mind, as expreſſed when his Majeſty was laſt in Council. In that Draught, the Free men (and not all Free-holders,) had Power to Chuſe the Deputy-Governour, and the other General Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: And the King's Governour had not a Negative Voice al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him in any Caſe.</p>
            <p>This Draught was preſented at the Council-Board on the Eighth Day of <hi>June</hi> laſt; when it was by ſome objected, That
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65598:6"/>by ſuch a Charter as this, the King's Governour would be made <hi>a Governor of Clouts;</hi> and Order was given to prepare new <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes,</hi> or <hi>Heads,</hi> for another Draught: Which indeed made the Charter deſigned to be <hi>no Charter of Incorporation,</hi> and did deprive the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> of ſome Eſſential Priviledges in their former Charter. When thoſe <hi>Minutes</hi> were agreed on by the Lords, the Secretary of the Committee gave me a Copy of them; with an Order from their Lordſhips, That if the <hi>Agents</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony</hi> were not ſatisfied therewith, they ſhould bring in their Objections to Mr. Attorney-General. I ſhewed the Order to the other <hi>Agents.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Aſhurſt</hi> went with me to the Attorney-General. I expreſſed my Diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, perhaps, with a greater <hi>Pathos</hi> than I ſhould have done, earneſtly proteſting, that I would ſooner part with my Life, than <hi>Conſent</hi> to the <hi>Minutes,</hi> or any thing elſe that did infringe any Liberty or Priviledge of Right belonging to my Countrey. The like I ſaid to ſome Miniſters of State: Who replied, That our <hi>Conſent</hi> was not expected nor deſired: For they did not think the <hi>Agents</hi> of <hi>New-England</hi> were <hi>Plenipotentiaries</hi> from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sovereign State; but that if we declared we would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the King's Pleaſure, his Majeſty was reſolved to ſettle the Countrey, and we muſt take what would follow.</p>
            <p>I drew up ſome Reaſons againſt the <hi>Minutes</hi> propoſed; Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Aſhurſt</hi> joyned with me therein; we argued, That the King had graciouſly promiſed a Reſtoration of Charter-Priviledges to <hi>New-England;</hi> and that Charter-Priviledges might with as much and more reaſon be with-held from any, or all the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations in <hi>England</hi> which were never legally Reſtored, as from <hi>New-England;</hi> with ſeveral other Arguments too large to be here inſerted. Thoſe Reaſons we delivered in Writing to the King's Attorney-General, who preſented them to the Lords at the Council-Board. I likewiſe cauſed a Copy of them to be ſent over to the King in <hi>Flanders:</hi> Moreover, ſome Great Ones at Court wrote to ſeveral of the Miniſters of State who were with the King, entreating them to uſe their Intereſt with his Majeſty, that nothing might be Impoſed on <hi>New-England,</hi> which would be grievous to his good Subjects there.</p>
            <p>Some were apt to think, that if the King were in <hi>England,</hi> we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65598:6"/>might prevail with his Majeſty to ſignifie his Diſallowance of thoſe <hi>Minutes</hi> which were ſo grievous to us; and that therefore it might not be amiſs to write to the King in <hi>Flanders,</hi> praying that a ſtop might be put to any further Proceedings about the Charter, until his Majeſty's happy Return to <hi>England.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a Great Perſon (whom I knew the Queen had an high Eſteem of) to pray her Majeſty to write to the King, That he would graciouſly pleaſe to Command that the Charter ſhould Paſs, as drawn up by the Attorney-General; or elſe that it ſhould be Deferred until his Majeſty's coming. The <hi>Queen</hi> was ſo kind as to do this for <hi>New-England.</hi> I now concluded that nothing more would be done for ſome Months.</p>
            <p>By continual Attendance on this arduous Affair, I had broken my Natural Reſt, and neglected my Neceſſary Food, inſomuch that my Health was greatly impaired: Phyſicians adviſed me to recede into the Countrey, and uſe Mineral Waters for my Recovery.</p>
            <p>Before I had been there long, I had (and was ſurprized at it) notice that the King had ſignified his Approbation of the <hi>Minutes</hi> which we were ſo much concerned about; and that it was his Royal Pleaſure that <hi>New-England</hi> ſhould be forthwith ſettled accordingly.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, a very great Man, and a great Friend of <hi>New-England,</hi> deſired a Perſon of Quality to adviſe me to take up with what was propoſed; withall adding, that if the King were in <hi>England,</hi> as Matters were now circumſtanced, nothing more or better could be expected. I immediately returned to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty's Principal Secretary of State aſſured me, that he had received ſuch a Signification of the King's Pleaſure as has been mentioned; and was pleaſed to let me ſee the Letter; wherein it was expreſsly declared, not only that the King did approve of the <hi>Minutes</hi> agreed unto by the Lords of the Committee; but that he did <hi>by no means approve</hi> of the <hi>Objections</hi> which the <hi>Agents</hi> of <hi>New-England</hi> had made againſt them.</p>
            <p>We then reſolved however to get as much Good, and prevent as much Hurt to the Countrey as poſſibly might be. A Petition was Signed by Sir <hi>Henry Aſhurſt</hi> and my ſelf, praying, That no Property belonging to that Colony, or to any therein, might by the <hi>New Charter</hi> be taken from them, nor any Priviledges which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65598:7"/>they had a Right unto: That the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Mayn</hi> might be Confirmed: <hi>Nova Scotia</hi> added to the <hi>Maſſachuſets:</hi> And, That <hi>New Hampſhire</hi> might be put under that Government. As to what concerns <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> we were told, the People there deſired to be under any Government in the World, rather than that of <hi>Maſſachuſets.</hi> Great Oppoſition was made againſt what was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed concerning the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Mayn,</hi> but at laſt it was granted; and <hi>Nova Scotia,</hi> ſo far as in the Charter is expreſſed. Juſt at this time, Letters came to my hand from <hi>Plymouth Colony,</hi> giving me the Thanks of the General Court there, for that I had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented their being annexed to <hi>New-York,</hi> (which was by ſome Perſons of Intereſt deſigned above a Year ago:) And intimating, That the generality of People there deſired to have a diſtinct Charter, and be confirmed as a diſtinct Government amongſt themſelves: But if that could not be obtained, that then, for the Lord's ſake, I would endeavour that they might be united to <hi>Boſton,</hi> rather than to <hi>New-York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I underſtood the Charter was finiſhed, and had been read before the Lords, I prayed that I might ſee it, and carry it to Councel; becauſe there might be ſome Clauſes in it which their Lordſhips might have ſuch Reaſons ſuggeſted to them, as they would think meet to expunge them, or to add ſome Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars which might be Beneficial to his Majeſty's Subjects in that Colony, and no ways Prejudicial to the King's Intereſt, nor yet inconſiſtent with thoſe <hi>Minutes</hi> which they would not ſuffer to be contradicted. This Requeſt was granted, only I muſt return the Copy within a few days: An Eminent Councellor peruſed it two or three times, and made his <hi>Remarks</hi> on it.</p>
            <p>That Phraſe of <hi>Corporal Oath</hi> was altered, that ſo no Snare might be laid before ſuch as ſcruple Swearing on the Book. A Clauſe was added, Confirming Grants made by the General Court, notwithſtanding any defect that might attend the Form of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance, that ſo Mens Titles to their Lands might not be invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated, only for that the Laws which gave them their Right, had not paſſed under the Publick Seal in the time of the former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Some other Alterations we prayed for, but we could not obtain them.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion now, was, <hi>Whether we ſhould ſubmit to this New Settlement? Or, in hopes of obtaining a Reverſion of the Judgment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65598:7"/>againſt the Old Charter, ſignifie to the Miniſters of State, that we had rather have no Charter at all, than ſuch an one as was now propoſed to acceptance?</hi> I knew that in the <hi>multitude of Councellors there is ſafety,</hi> and did therefore adviſe with many, and with Perſons Unprejudiced, and of the greateſt Wiſdom and Ability to judge; with Noblemen, Genlemen, Divines, and Lawyers: They all agreed, that it was not only Lawful, but, all Circumſtances conſidered, a <hi>Duty</hi> to ſubmit to what was now offered. Some ſaid, They were very weak Men, and unfit to appear as <hi>Agents</hi> for a <hi>Colony,</hi> that ſhould make any Queſtion of it. Others ſaid, That a peremptory Refuſal would bring not only a greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, but a fatal Ruine on <hi>New-England;</hi> and then Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind would lay the blame on the Weakneſs and Wilfulneſs of the <hi>Agents,</hi> who when they could not have what they would, ought to ſubmit to what they could get. The Opinion of the Lawyers, was, That ſuch a Paſſive Submiſſion was not a Surrender, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as nothing was done under Hand and Seal: Nor could there be a Surrender in this caſe, ſince Judgment was already Entred and Recorded againſt the Old Charter: Nor were the <hi>Agents</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Surrendring, as not being <hi>Plenipotentiaries;</hi> and that their taking up with this, did not make the People in that Colony, in Law, uncapable of obtaining all their Old Priviledges, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a favourable Opportunity ſhould preſent it ſelf; for the World knew, that in a preſent parting with any of their ancient Rights, they were forced to yield unto Neceſſity. I remember, an Honeſt Lawyer, and a Well-wiſher to <hi>New-England,</hi> told me, That if we were put to our Choice, whether to enjoy our <hi>Old Charter</hi> (which he was well acquainted with) again, juſt as it was, or to take up with this, (all things duely conſidered,) we were not wiſe if we did not chuſe <hi>this</hi> rather than <hi>that.</hi> It was conſidered, That a Judgment (right or wrong) not in Court of <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> but in <hi>Chancery,</hi> ſtanding on Record againſt the <hi>Charter</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachuſets,</hi> whereby it was vacated and annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, <hi>that</hi> Colony was fallen into the Kings Hands; ſo that he might put them under what Governours, or what Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment he ſhould pleaſe. Their <hi>Agents</hi> might beg for a full Reſtitution of all Ancient Priviledges, but they might not either Chuſe or Refuſe as to them ſhould ſeem beſt. It was conſidered, That there was no probability of obtaining a Reverſion of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65598:8"/>Judgment againſt the former Charter. We ſaw it was in vain to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to bring it out of <hi>Chancery</hi> into the Court of <hi>King's Bench.</hi> There were thoughts of bringing the Matter into the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> by a Writ of Error in Judgment; but it was believed that no <hi>Curſitor</hi> would now venture to Sign a Writ of Error; and that if he ſhould, the <hi>Lords</hi> would not be forward to concern themſelves in this Affair.</p>
            <p>Although the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canturbury</hi> that now is, and many of the preſent Biſhops, are Friends to <hi>New-England,</hi> (as well as to all good Men,) and I have cauſe to acknowledge the perſonal Reſpect I have received from many of them: And although a great Intereſt has been made for <hi>New-England</hi> amongſt the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Lords; nevertheleſs, when they ſhould underſtand that the King was deſirous to have that Countrey put under another Form of Government, which his Royal Wiſdom judged would be better for them than what they formerly enjoyed, the Lords would be very ſlow in doing any thing that they knew would be diſſatisfactory to his Majeſty. And if they ſhould ſee cauſe to take the Caſe of <hi>New-England</hi> into their Conſideration, though they would not Juſtifie the manner of Proceedings; yet when they ſhould hear all that was to be Objected againſt the Governour and Company, on the Account of their having exceeded the Powers of their Charter in ſeveral Particulars, and in a very high degree, they would certainly judge that they had merited a Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. It was alſo Conſidered, That the Old Charter was, in more reſpects than one, very defective: For by that, the <hi>Government</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> had no more Power than <hi>Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in <hi>England</hi> have. But thoſe Corporations have not Power in <hi>Capital Caſes.</hi> Both the Judges and Eminent Lawyers have aſſured me, that though Power was given to Corporations in <hi>Criminal,</hi> except <hi>Capital Caſes be particularly expreſsed,</hi> their Power does not reach ſo far: Nor was there any thing in the Old Charter concerning an <hi>Houſe of Deputies,</hi> or <hi>Aſſembly of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives:</hi> Nor had the Governour and Company Power to impoſe Taxes on the Inhabitants: Nor to Erect <hi>Courts of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty,</hi> &amp;c. The King's Attorney-General (who is no Enemy to <hi>New-England</hi>) declared, the two Chief Juſtices, and Sollicitor-General, concurring with him, That ſuppoſing the Judgment againſt the Charter of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> to be Reverſed, if the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65598:8"/>ſhould exert ſuch Powers as before the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> againſt their Charter they had done, there would now be a Writ of <hi>Scire facias</hi> iſſued out againſt them in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and their Charter-Priviledges would undoubtedly be taken from them. And it was Conſidered, That if the Judgment againſt the Old Charter had been Reverſed by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony</hi> would, for all that, have been in a far more miſerable Condition than by the preſent Settlement they are reduced unto: For then the <hi>Province of Mayn,</hi> as to Government, would have been taken from them, ſince Government is a Truſt that cannot be ſold; and <hi>Hampſhire</hi> (which would have been made to extend as far as <hi>Salem,</hi>) and <hi>Plymouth,</hi> would have been put under a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſent from <hi>England;</hi> which Governour would have had the Command over the Militia, and the Power of Admiralty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony:</hi> So that, in fine, <hi>Boſton</hi> would have been deprived of Trade, and the whole Colony made very inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant: And if they had exerted Powers neceſſary for the Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their Government, perpetual Conplaints would have been made againſt them. It was moreover Conſidered, That if the Agents of that Colony had ſignified to the Miniſters of State, that they had rather have no Charter at all, than this which the King was pleaſed to grant to them, the Conſequence would have been, that they ſhould have had a Governour wholly a Stranger to <hi>New-England,</hi> and a Deputy-Governour not acceptable to the People there; and many of his Councellors Strangers, and others of them ſuch as were <hi>Androſs</hi>'s Creatures; and that this Governour ſhould have had the ſame Power which the Governours in other Plantations have, to Appoint the General Officers. They are very weak Men that doubt of this; and if they will look no further than their Neighbours at <hi>New-York</hi> and <hi>Virginia,</hi> they may ſee De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations before their Eyes ſufficient to convince them. It was likewiſe Conſidered, That ſome Perſons in <hi>London</hi> were endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get a <hi>Pattent</hi> for all <hi>Mines, Minerals, Gums, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>New-England:</hi> Which Deſign was, of late, likely to have taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, only the New Charter has moſt happily prevented that which would have been of pernicious Conſequence to all that Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory. It was further Conſidered, That by this <hi>New Charter</hi> great Priviledges are granted to the People in <hi>New-England,</hi> and, in ſome Particulars, greater than they formerly enjoyed: For all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65598:9"/>
               <hi>Engliſh Liberties</hi> are reſtored to them: No Perſons ſhall have a Penny of their Eſtates taken from them; nor any Laws impoſed on them, without their own Conſent by Repreſentatives choſen by themſelves. Religion is ſecured; for Liberty is granted to all Men to Worſhip God after that manner which in their Conſciences they ſhall be perſwaded is the moſt Scriptural way. The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court may by Laws Encourage and Protect that <hi>Religion</hi> which is the general Profeſſion of the Inhabitants there. They may ſtill have <hi>Judges, as at the firſt;</hi> and <hi>Councellors, as at the beginning,</hi> if the fault be not their own. As long as their Principal Magiſtrates, Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, are ſuch as will encourage Vertue and Piety, and puniſh Vice, Religion will flouriſh: And if they have not ſuch, the fault will not be in the <hi>New-Charter,</hi> but in themſelves; ſince no bad Councellor, Judge, or Juſtice of the Peace, can now be impoſed on them. Theſe things are as a Wall of Defence about the Lord's Vineyard in that part of the World. The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Court (now that the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony</hi> is made a <hi>Province</hi>) hath, with the King's Approbation, as much Power in <hi>New-England,</hi> as the King and Parliament have in <hi>England;</hi> which is more than could be ſaid in the time of the former Government there, which had only the Power of a Corporation. The General Court has now Power to impoſe Taxes upon all the Inhabitants; and to make Laws which ſhall Incorporate Towns, or Schools of Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which by the Firſt Charter they had not Power to do. That Countrey may now expect Protection and Aſſiſtance from <hi>England,</hi> as the Matter ſhall require, more than formerly. And although there are ſome things in this <hi>New Charter</hi> which are not deſirable, yet nothing that is intolerable. Take it with all its Faults, and it is not ſo bad, but that when I left <hi>New-England,</hi> the Inhabitants of that Territory would gladly have parted with many a Thouſand Pound to have obtained one ſo good. The great fear, is, that though at preſent there be a good Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour (appointed by the King,) who wiſheth well to <hi>New-England;</hi> yet he will quickly be removed, and perhaps an Enemy come in his room. But I am morally certain of it, that if they hearken to the Advice of their beſt Friends, no Perſon not agreeable to <hi>New-England,</hi> in reſpect of Religion, and the Temper of that People, will be ſet over them, during their preſent Majeſties Reign, whom the God of Heaven ſend long to Live and Reign.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65598:9"/>Yet ſuppoſe it ſhould be otherwiſe: Suppoſe a Perſon as bad as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droſs</hi> (and the <hi>New-Englanders</hi> think there can hardly be a worſe,) ſhould come amongſt them, What can he do? He cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conſent of the Council Choſen by the Repreſentatives of the People, appoint a Sheriff to pack Juries to ſerve his turn; nor Judges that will act againſt their Conſciences, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than diſpleaſe him. Nor can he now ſend Men out of the Countrey, without their own conſent. Nor can he and his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures make Laws, or Leavy Taxes; nor Invade any Man's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, under pretence that it is the King's; and that they muſt come to him for Patents, that ſo they may have a true Title to their Lands and Eſtates. Nor can he, without violating the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> diſturb any Man for his Religion. The King's Governour has a Negative Voice in all Acts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; which may be thought a great Infringement of the Peoples Liberty; and indeed, makes the Civil Government of <hi>New-England</hi> more <hi>Monarchical,</hi> and leſs <hi>Democratical,</hi> than in former Times. Nevertheleſs, <hi>the People have a Negative on him.</hi> In which reſpect, <hi>New-England</hi> is by this Charter more priviledged than <hi>Ireland,</hi> and than any Engliſh Plantation whatſoever, or than they that live in <hi>England</hi> it ſelf are. Appeals to <hi>England</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by this <hi>New Charter;</hi> but only in <hi>Perſonal</hi> (not in Real or Mixed) <hi>Actions,</hi> where the matter of difference is above Three hundred Pounds Sterling in value. So that as to Titles of Land there cannot be any Appeal to <hi>England,</hi> but thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies are to have a final Determination in Courts of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture amongſt themſelves. And Laws Enacted by the <hi>General Court,</hi> are to be tranſmitted to the King for his Royal Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Nevertheleſs, thoſe Laws, when made, are to be in force as ſoon as made, until ſuch time as diſallowed of by the King: And if within the ſpace of Three Years the King's Diſapproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be not ſignified, thoſe Laws are to be Perpetual, except by the General Court they ſhall be Repealed. By the Old Charter, the Governour and Company might not make any Laws contrary to the Laws of <hi>England:</hi> And ſuch reaſonable Laws as are not contrary thereto, will no doubt be Confirmed by his Majeſty, if the People in <hi>New-England</hi> be not wanting to themſelves as to due Endeavours that it may be ſo. All theſe things duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, the Beſt and Wiſeſt Men in <hi>England</hi> thought that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65598:10"/>Perſons who were concerned for <hi>New-England,</hi> would do an ill Service for their Countrey, if they ſhould peremptorily decline a Submiſſion to this Settlement, and thereby bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that which would be more undeſirable.</p>
            <p>I muſt beg leave (for it is a Truth) to ſay this further, That whereas the People in <hi>New-England</hi> have not obtained all the Charter-Priviledges which they have at ſeveral times Petitioned Their Majeſties for; they have more reaſon to blame themſelves, than thoſe of their Agents, who did their utmoſt to procure every thing for them which they prayed for. Had they at the time of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> entred upon the <hi>full Exerciſe of their Old Charter-Government,</hi> and then humbly ſignified to the King that they had ſo done; and that they were perſwaded, His Majeſty, who declared, when Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> That Charters and Ancient Priviledges ſhould be reſtored to the Engliſh Nation in general, would not be offended at them on the account of their adhering to what was their undoubted Right; wiſe Men are of Opinion that they might have gone on without diſturbance, until ſuch time as new Complaints ſhould be exhibited againſt them, on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of doing things which by their Charter they were never impowered to do. But in an Addreſs to the King, they aſſure his Majeſty, That <hi>they had not entred upon the full Exerciſe of their Charter-Government; but that not having received Directions from</hi> England, <hi>which they humbly waited for, they entred upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Preſervation of the Peace, until ſuch time as they ſhould receive an Orderly Settlement from</hi> England; <hi>which they prayed might be according to their Old Charter, that had been unrighteouſly taken from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when wiſe Men in <hi>London</hi> ſaw this: Will you (ſaid they) who are Agents for the <hi>Maſſachuſets Colony,</hi> refuſe to ſubmit to a Settlement of your Government from <hi>England,</hi> when your Principals have ſignified to the King that they will do it? Who gave you that Power of Refuſal? Has the General Court, in an Addreſs to the King, declared, They have not entred on the full Exerciſe of their Charter-Government, but that they wait for the King's Pleaſure, as to their Settlement; then ſurely they have not given you private Inſtructions not to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit? And if they have not, you cannot anſwer your Refuſal to your Principals, nor to the King, nor to Mankind. Have not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65598:10"/>your Magiſtrates cauſed a new Clauſe to be added to the uſual Oath taken by the Aſſiſtants, <hi>viz.</hi> That if <hi>contrary Orders ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive from England,</hi> that Oath ſhall not oblige them to ſerve as Aſſiſtants until the Year be expired? Shall then their Agents pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt ſuch Orders?</p>
            <p>Such as theſe have been the Reaſonings of wiſe Men in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Moreover, the Government in <hi>New-England</hi> Petitioned the King to aſſiſt them with Frigats, and Supplies of Arms and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; which was, in effect, to pray for a Governour. They could not be ſo weak, to think the King would ſend the one without the other.</p>
            <p>When I wrote to this purpoſe to a principal Perſon in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there; the Anſwer returned to me, was, That I, and other Perſons that were employed as Agents for that Colony, ought to look on it as the principal thing committed to our Care and Truſt; and that, <hi>preferrable to all other things whatſoever:</hi> To endeavour the obtaining Aſſiſtance from their Majeſties, againſt the <hi>French,</hi> and other Enemies; and that this was the ſence of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the ſober People in <hi>New-England.</hi> So that if theſe two came in Competition, either to have the Old Charter juſt as it was, or to get Aſſiſance from <hi>England;</hi> we were told we ſhould be Unfaithful to our Truſt, if we did not preferr the latter to the former.</p>
            <p>Yet further: The Countrey was ſo impoveriſhed by the Wars made upon them, as that they could not ſend a competent Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to their Agents for the management of their Affair.</p>
            <p>Beſides what was ſent to me out of <hi>New-England,</hi> I expended upwards of Two Hundred Pounds of my own Perſonal Eſtate, out of Love to that People. And I did, for their ſakes, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of a Merchant in <hi>London</hi> above Three Hundred Pounds more, which was Two Years before care was taken for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of it.</p>
            <p>The laſt Year, ſome who were hearty Well-wiſhers to <hi>New-England,</hi> wrote thither, That they muſt conſider, their Life, their Religion, the Welfare of their Poſterity for ever, depended on a ſuitable Suppy for their Agents that were concerned in Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting their great Affairs at Court. This, notwithſtanding, for more than a Twelvemonth, not one Penny was returned: So that I was neceſſitated, either to ſuffer Ruine to come upon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65598:11"/>Countrey where I had ſpent the greateſt part of my Life, or elſe muſt borrow Money again to ſerve them: Which I did, and Engaged all the Eſtate I have in the World for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment thereof: This is more than ever any man did before me, and perhaps more than any Perſon ſo Circumſtanced as I have bin, will do after me.</p>
            <p>And what was I able to do more? I do humbly affirm, That there is not a man in this World, that has done more, nor ſo much, towards the obtaining of a full Reſtitution of all Charter-Priviledges to <hi>New-England,</hi> as I have done. And as to the undeſirable Minutes in the New Charter, there is no perſon living that has manifeſted his diſſent therefrom, or more oppoſed, or done more to prevent them, than I have: But to reject all the Good therein, becauſe of ſome things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, is that which I dared not to be guilty of. As Day and Night have ſeen it, ſo I can, and I do appeal to Heaven and Earth, that I have ſerved that People with all Fidelity to the very utmoſt of my Power.</p>
            <p>And now they muſt give me leave to give them the beſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I can. I ſhall not need (for they will do it of themſelves) to perſwade them to ſend an Addreſs of Humble Thanks to their Majeſties, for their Royal Favour in Reſtoring Property, and in Conferring greater Priviledges on <hi>New-England,</hi> than have bin granted to any other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantation. And for that their Majeſties have been graciouſly pleaſed to put the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government of <hi>New-England</hi> into good hands. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Nominated for Governour (Sir <hi>William Phipps</hi>) is one that has ventured his Life to ſerve his Countrey. When <hi>Gideon</hi> did ſo, the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were deſirous that he ſhould Rule over them: The Deputy-Governour, Mr. <hi>Stoughton,</hi> is one whoſe worth is known in both <hi>Englands.</hi> One of more than ordinary Accompliſhments, both as to parts Natural and Acquired, and as to Vertue and Integrity. And as for the Twenty Eight Aſſiſtants, who are appointed to be of the Governours Council, every man of them is a Friend to <hi>New-England,</hi> and to the Churches and Intereſt of Chriſt therein. To be in the hands of ſuch Rulers is an invaluable Mercy.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65598:11"/>
            <p>As for me, whom the Lord Jeſus has made uſe of as an Inſtrument in his Hand, for obtaining this Mercy for <hi>New-England;</hi> I deſire no Acknowledgment, nor any Reward in the leaſt, for the Difficult and Expenſive Service I have for their ſakes gone through. Let me wait for my Recompenſe till the Reſurrection of the Juſt. But if that People be not thankful to God, and to the King and Queen, for what has been done for them; not only the King and Queen, but the Majeſty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, may juſtly be incenſed againſt them. To be thankful for what is given, is the way to receive more from God and Men.</p>
            <p>But let me Propoſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>General Court</hi> do, without delay, agree upon a Body of Good Laws. They may make ſuch Laws for the Settlement of the Militia, and for the ſecuring of Liberty to the Subject, as ſhall be better than their Old Charter. And as to what concerns the Upholding of Religion in that Countrey, there are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Two things which may be done. The one, is, By Laws to Encourage an Able and Faithful Miniſtry. The other, is, To take care that the <hi>Colledge</hi> be Confirmed in ſuch Hands, as will make it their Concern to Promote and Propagate Vertue and Learning. It was in a ſpecial manner with reſpect thereunto, that I did undertake a Voyage for <hi>England</hi> above Three Years and an half ſince. As long as that Countrey lay unſettled, as to the Civil Government, I could not do much for the Colledge; only I prevailed with a Gentleman of my Acquaintance, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath a Legacy of Five Hundred Pounds to that Society. And now, in this <hi>New-Charter,</hi> all Donations or Revenues granted to that Academy, are by the King, under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> Confirmed. I humbly propoſed to ſome great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, That a particular Charter might be granted for the Incorporating that School for Academical Learning. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was made, That it ſhould be ſo, if I deſired it: But that a better way would be, for the <hi>General Court</hi> of the <hi>Maſſachu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets Colony,</hi> by a Law, to Incorporate their Colledge; and to make it an Univerſity, with as ample Priviledges as they ſhould think neceſſary; and then tranſmit that <hi>Act of the General Court</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> for the Royal Approbation; which would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65598:12"/>be obtained. I look upon this Particular alone, to be well worth my going to <hi>England,</hi> and there ſerving half an Apprenticeſhip; for that no ſmall Concernment of Religion, and the Happineſs of future Generations, are comprehended in this Matter reſpecting the Colledge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I take it to be good Advice, That Judges, Sheriffs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, ſhould be Eſtabliſhed throughout the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, of ſuch as are Men fearing God; and that their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions continue, <hi>Quam diu ſe benè geſſerint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However it ſhall be, whether my Counſels be followed or not, or whether my ſincere Intentions, and unwearied Endeavours to ſerve <hi>New-England,</hi> find Acceptance with them or no, I have this to comfort my ſelf with, That God has been ſo gracious to me, as to make me inſtrumental in obtaining for my Countrey a <hi>MAGNA CHARTA,</hi> whereby Religion, and Engliſh Liberties, with ſome peculiar Priviledges, Liberties, and all Mens Properties, are Confirmed and Secured (Allowance being given for the Inſtability of all Humane Affairs) to Them and their Poſterity for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>LONDON,</hi> 
                  <date>Novemb. 16. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>INCREASE MATHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65598:12"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT of a LETTER (WRITTEN By ſome of the moſt Eminent <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt Divines</hi> in <hi>London,</hi>) Concerning the NEW CHARTER Granted to the Colony of <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> in <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the much Honoured <hi>General Court</hi> Aſſembled at <hi>Boſton,</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Much Honoured Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE muſt give this true Teſtimony of our much Eſteemed and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brother, Mr. <hi>Increaſe Mather,</hi> That with inviolate Integrity, excellent Prudence, and unfainting Diligence, he has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged the great Buſineſs committed to his Truſt. As he is inſtructed in the School of Heaven, to miniſter in the Affairs of the Soul; ſo he is furniſht with a Talent, to tranſact Affairs of State. His Proceedings have been with that Caution and Circumſpection, as is correſpondent to the weight of his Commiſſion. He with Courage and Conſtancy has purſued the Noble Scope of his Employment; and underſtanding the true Moment of things, has preferred the Publick Good to the vain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of ſome, that more might have been obtained, if peremptorily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on. Conſidering the open Oppoſition, and ſecret Arts, that have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65598:13"/>been uſed to fruſtrate the beſt Endeavours for the Intereſt of <hi>New-England,</hi> the happy Iſſue of things is ſuperiour to our Expectations. Your preſent <hi>Charter</hi> ſecures Liberty and Property, the faireſt Flowers of the Civil State: And which is incomparably more valuable, it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures the enjoyment of the bleſſed Goſpel in its Purity and Freedom. Although there is a reſtraint of your Power in ſome things that were granted in your former Charter; yet there are ſome ample Priviledges in other things, that may be of perpetual Advantage to the Colony.</p>
            <p>We doubt not but your faithful <hi>Agent</hi> will receive a gracious Reward Above; and we hope his ſucceſsful Service will be welcom'd with your entire Approbation, and grateful Acceptance.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>LONDON, <date>
                     <hi>Octob. 17. 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>We are, Your very Humble, And Faithful Servants, <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Bates,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Woodcock,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthew Mead,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthew Barker,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Stretton,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vincent Alſop,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Howe,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John James,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Samuel Anneſly,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Griffith,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Mayo,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iſaac Chauncey,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Quick.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65598:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
